Register of the Poland. Ambasada (France) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ambasada (France) records,
1919-1945
45004
Poland. Ambasada (France)
23 manuscript boxes (9.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records, relating to Franco-Polish relations in the interwar period and during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1945
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (24 reels).
Historical Note
Polish embassy in France.
Scope and Content Note
The Polish embassy in France, considered the most important link in the Polish diplomatic network, officially opened in 1924, with Alfred Chlapowski as ambassador until 1936. Before then, the interests of the Poles after World War I were represented by the Polish National Committee (Polski Komitet Narodowy), responsible for Polish relations with the members of the Triple Entente. Dissolved in 1919, the Committee was replaced by a legation, headed by Maurycy Zamoyski. He remained at his post until 1924, when, by decree of the Council of Ministers, the legation's status was raised to that of an embassy.
From the very beginning the embassy played an extremely important role in Poland's foreign policy, particularly in the second half of the 1920s and throughout the 1930s. In charge during the most critical years of 1936-1939 was Ambassador Juliusz Lukasiewicz, an experienced diplomat of great political skills as well as a talented organizer; he was also a close associate and personal friend of the foreign minister, Jozef Beck.
This collection is an excellent illustration of those tense years, as can be seen in the telegrams exchanged with the Foreign Ministry headquarters in Warsaw and with many Polish diplomatic posts. They describe various shifts in Polish-French relations, reflected in talks and treaties, both military and diplomatic. What might be of most interest to the researcher here is the rapprochement between the two countries in the years preceding World War II: Poland then had in France a very close ally, a much more important one than Great Britain.
With the collapse of the Polish state in 1939 and the government's move to France, Ambassador Lukasiewicz was replaced by Feliks Frankowski, who kept his rank of chargé d'affaires and that of minister plenipotentiary. He also represented Poland under the Vichy government until September of 1940, when, because of strong German pressure, Poles lost their diplomatic accreditation to France and the embassy moved to Lisbon. (Later, with the same titles, Frankowski represented Poland to the French National Committee in Algiers.)
Due to the lack of Polish diplomatic representation on French territory, responsibilities for assistance to Poles were assumed by Stanislaw Zabiello, the representative of the Polish Red Cross (Polski Czerwony Krzyz). Information on his incredible and still largely unknown accomplishments can be found among the Polish Foreign Ministry (Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych) records, also in the Hoover Archives, particularly documents related to welfare work of the embassy and operations of the Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare.
As reflected in the records of the embassy, one of the major concerns of the Polish authorities, especially after June 1940, was the fate of over 600 thousand displaced Polish nationals, a large percentage of them Jewish. Poles constituted the biggest foreign community in France, having traditionally settled there in large numbers. These immigrants, refugees, and displaced persons, in addition to the thousands of former soldiers who left occupied Poland, contributed to the formation of a large army in France. Many of those who didn't continue their odyssey joined the underground, and eventually became subject to Nazi persecution and deportations.
After 1940, the Polish authorities in London maintained delicate contacts with the Free French. The difficult relations between the two sides were due to the complex situation within the French Underground and De Gaulle's entourage. Nevertheless, diplomatic relations were maintained, and in 1944, the post of ambassador was restored, with Kajetan Dzierzykraj Morawski in charge until 1945.
This collection was transferred to the Hoover Institution in two parts, in 1945 and 1959. In the early 1990s, records of the embassy were also identified within the Polish Foreign Ministry collection and merged with the original two deposits.
Besides the Hoover Institution, records of the embassy are stored in three other locations: the Archiwum Akt Nowych in Warsaw (particularly for the years 1919-1924), the Pilsudski Institute in New York (for a small portion of the Lukasiewicz papers), and the Sikorski Institute in London (for a large portion of Morawski's papers, of which there are just a few here at Hoover).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; France.; France--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--France.
Series Description
- Ambassador File, 1925-1939. (Box 1)
  Agreements, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other material relating to the operations of the office of ambassador. Arranged chronologically
- Military Attache File, 1925-1945. (Box 1-2)
  Announcements, circulars, correspondence, memoranda, receipts, reports and other material relating to the military affairs of various branches of Polish military forces, military alliance with France, formation and evacuation of Polish Forces from France. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Minister of Foreign Affairs File, 1931-1945. (Box 2-5)
  Circulars, correspondence, notes, reports, transcripts of talks relating to the Polish-French relations and operations of the Polish Government-in-Exile in London. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Office of Emigration Counselor File, 1928-1937. (Box 5)
  Correspondence and personal files relating to the affairs of Poles abroad before the outbreak of World War II. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Refugees File, 1940-1942. (Box 6)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and reports relating to the circumstances of demobilization and transfer of population from France under German occupation. Arranged chronologically
- Relations with France File, 1941-1943. (Box 6-7)
  Bulletins, correspondence, reports relating to the Polish-French diplomatic relations with the Free French and the Vichy government during World War II
- Budget File, 1936-1943. (Box 7-10)
  Applications, circulars, correspondence, inventories, ledgers, receipts, reports relating to the financial operations of the Polish government. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Correspondence, 1937-1945. (Box 11)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Telegrams, 1919-1940. (Box 11-23)
  Arranged alphabetically by place of origin and destination and therein chronologically
- Printed Matter, 1941-1943. (Box 23)
  Bulletins and code books. Arranged alphabetically
Container List
- AMBASSADOR FILE, 1925-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1925. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes Polish-French military agreement
  - 1929 (Folder 1: 2)
  - 1930 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1931 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1933 (Folder 1: 5)
  - 1934 (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1936 (Folder 1: 7)
  - 1939 (Folder 1: 8)
- MILITARY ATTACHE FILE, 1925-1945
  - General
    - 1925 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1927 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1928 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1929 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1945
      - January-February (Folder 1: 13)
      - April-May (Folder 1: 14)
      - June (Folder 1: 15)
  - Budget
    - Payroll
      - General, 1939-1940 (Folder 1: 16)
      - Delegat Cywilny Ambasady RP do Spraw Wojskowych, Centralne Biuro Rekrutacyjne (Embassy's Civilian Delegate of Military Affairs, Central Recruitment Bureau) (Folder 1: 17)
    - Receipts, 1940
      - January-March (Folder 1: 18)
      - April-June (Folder 1: 19)
  - Pomocnicza Sluzba Kobiet (Women's Military Auxiliary), 1944-1945
    - General (Folder 1: 20)
    - Announcements (Folder 1: 21)
  - Recruitment of civilians (Box 2)
    - General
      - 1944 October-November (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1945
        - January-February (Folder 2: 2)
        - March (Folder 2: 3)
        - April. (Folder 2: 4)
          Situation report
    - Lublin Committee, 1945 March-May (Folder 2: 5)
    - Miners, 1944 December - 1945 May (Folder 2: 6)
    - Poles in German army (Folder 2: 7)
  - Second Division in Switzerland, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 8)
- MINISTER OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS FILE, 1931-1945
  - General
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1940 (Folder 2: 9)
      - Halifax, Edward Frederick (Folder 2: 10)
      - Hlond, August (Folder 2: 11)
      - Modzelewski, Jan, 1940 (Folder 2: 12)
      - Sikorski, Wladyslaw, 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 13)
      - Wieniawa-Dlugoszowski, Boleslaw (Folder 2: 14)
    - Notes
      - General
        - 1940
          - May (Folder 2: 15)
          - June (Folder 2: 16)
          - July (Folder 2: 17)
          - August (Folder 2: 18)
          - September (Folder 2: 19)
          - October. (Box-folder 3: 1)
            Includes Frankowski's note on transfer to Lisbon
          - November (Folder 3: 2)
          - December (Folder 3: 3)
        - 1941
          - January (Folder 3: 4)
          - February (Folder 3: 5)
          - March. (Folder 3: 6)
            Includes note on talks with De Gaulle
          - April (Folder 3: 7)
          - May (Folder 3: 8)
          - June (Folder 3: 9)
          - July. (Folder 3: 10)
            Includes note on transfer of gold
          - August (Folder 3: 11)
          - September. (Folder 3: 12)
            Includes note on talks with De Gaulle and French-Soviet relations
          - October (Folder 3: 13)
          - November (Folder 3: 14)
          - December (Folder 3: 15)
        - 1942
          - January (Folder 3: 16)
          - February (Folder 3: 17)
          - March (Folder 3: 18)
          - April (Folder 3: 19)
          - May (Folder 3: 20)
          - June (Folder 3: 21)
          - July (Folder 3: 22)
          - August (Folder 3: 23)
          - September (Folder 4: 1)
          - October (Folder 4: 2)
          - November (Folder 4: 3)
          - December (Folder 4: 4)
        - 1943 January-May (Folder 4: 5)
      - Crimes against humanity, German, 1941 (Folder 4: 6)
      - France - Colonies - World War, 1939-1945 (Folder 4: 7)
      - Mohl, Aleksander, 1941-1943 (Folder 4: 8)
      - Poklewski-Koziell, A., 1940 (Folder 4: 9)
      - Poland - Relations - France
        - Agreements from 1921 and 1940 (Folder 4: 10)
        - Documents, 1931-1935 (Folder 4: 11)
      - Ukraine, 1940 (Folder 4: 12)
      - World War, 1939-1945 - Aims and objectives - Poland, 1940 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Reports
      - General
        - Hitler, Adolf. Talks, speeches, interviews, statements, 1933-1939 (Folder 4: 14)
        - Poland, Conditions in
          - General, 1945 January-June (Folder 4: 15)
          - Biuletyn informacyjny, 1945 March-May (Folder 4: 16)
          - Popielow, Andrzej and Maciej, 1945 (Folder 4: 17)
        - Poles and their politics in Great Britain. Report by J. H. Rettinger, 1939 (Folder 4: 18)
      - Poland. Ambasada (France). Report on its archives, 1940 (Folder 4: 19)
      - Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych, 1942 April-July (Folder 4: 20)
      - Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych. "Conférence des représentants des pays occupés par l'ennemi, tenue à Londres du 5 au 21 novembre 1941 au Ministère des Affaires Étrangères de la République de Pologne: Procès-verbaux des séances," 1941 (Folder 4: 21)
    - Transcripts of talks between Poland and Great Britain, 1939-1940 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Communist government, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Poland - Foreign relations
    - Catholic Church, 1944 (Folder 5: 2)
    - France, 1945 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Great Britain, 1945 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Lithuania, 1945 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Soviet Union, 1939 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Switzerland, 1945 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Turkey, 1945 (Folder 5: 8)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, 1943 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Yalta Conference (1945) (Folder 5: 10)
- OFFICE OF EMIGRATION COUNSELOR (BIURO RADCY EMIGRACYJNEGO) FILE, 1928-1937
  - General
    - 1935. (Folder 5: 11)
      Includes frequent references to Jan Roskosz
    - 1936 (Folder 5: 12)
    - 1937 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Personal files
    - Cmela, Wladyslaw
      - 1928-1930 (Folder 5: 14)
      - 1932 (Folder 5: 15)
      - 1933-1935 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Dabrowska, Janina (Folder 5: 17)
    - Danilowicz, Kazimierz (Folder 5: 18)
    - Dankowka, Stefania (Folder 5: 19)
    - Daszkiewicz, Stefania (Folder 5: 20)
    - Dawidowicz, Maria (Folder 5: 21)
    - Dorzak, Alojzy (Folder 5: 22)
    - Drejer, Jan (Folder 5: 23)
    - Dressler, Janina (Folder 5: 24)
    - Drozio, Maria (Folder 5: 25)
    - Duraj, Henryk (Folder 5: 26)
    - Dzierzecka, Helena (Folder 5: 27)
    - Faber, Jozef (Folder 5: 28)
    - Fask, Maria (Folder 5: 29)
    - Fischoeder, Klara (Folder 5: 30)
    - Fonberg, Maria (Folder 5: 31)
- REFUGEES FILE, 1940-1942 (Box 6)
  - 1940.
    Includes references to demobilization
    - August (Folder 6: 1)
    - September (Folder 6: 2)
    - November-December (Folder 6: 3)
  - 1941 (Folder 6: 4)
  - 1942 (Folder 6: 5)
- RELATIONS WITH FRANCE FILE, 1941-1943
  - Free French
    - General
      - Journal officiel du commandement en chef français, 1943 (Folder 6: 6)
      - Journal officiel du haut commissariat de France en Afrique, 1943 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Algeria. Delegat Rzeczypospolitej na Afrykę, Emeryk Hutten-Czapski.
      Includes correspondence on gold
      - 1942 (Folder 6: 8)
      - 1943
        - January-March (Folder 6: 9)
        - April-July (Folder 6: 10)
    - London
      - General
        - General
          - 1941
            - January-June (Folder 6: 11)
            - July-December (Folder 6: 12)
          - 1942
            - January-June (Folder 6: 13)
            - July-December (Folder 6: 14)
          - 1943 January-July (Folder 6: 15)
        - Alliance Française. Fédération Britannique des Comités de l'Alliance Française. Bulletin, 1941 (Box-folder 7: 1)
        - Journal officiel de la France Combattante: Lois et décrêts, 1941-1943 (Folder 7: 2)
        - La Lettre de la France Libre, 1941 (Folder 7: 3)
        - Przegląd Prasy Francuskiej w Wielkiej Brytanii, 1941 (Folder 7: 4)
      - Comités franco-polonais, 1941-1942 (Folder 7: 5)
      - Polish government policy toward, 1941-1943 (Folder 7: 6)
      - Recognition of, 1941 September-October
        - General (Folder 7: 7)
        - Members and representatives, 1941 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Vichy.
    Includes representation transferred to Lisbon
    - General
      - 1940
        - General (Folder 7: 9)
        - Finances, June-October. (Folder 7: 10)
          Includes correspondence related to the transfer of Polish gold
      - 1941
        - January (Folder 7: 11)
        - February (Folder 7: 12)
        - March-April (Folder 7: 13)
        - May-June (Folder 7: 14)
        - July-December (Folder 7: 15)
      - 1942 (Folder 7: 16)
      - 1943. (Folder 7: 17)
        Includes Comité Français de la Libération Nationale
    - Les documents français, 1940 December. (Folder 7: 18)
      Marshal Pétain's government's decrees on the new economic order
- BUDGET FILE, 1936-1943
  - General
    - General, 1940 February-May (Folder 7: 19)
    - Correspondence
      - 1940
        - January-June (Folder 7: 20)
        - July (Folder 7: 21)
        - August (Folder 7: 22)
        - September (Folder 7: 23)
      - 1941
        - January (Folder 8: 1)
        - February (Folder 8: 2)
        - March (Folder 8: 3)
        - April (Folder 8: 4)
        - May (Folder 8: 5)
        - June (Folder 8: 6)
        - July (Folder 8: 7)
        - August (Folder 8: 8)
        - September (Folder 8: 9)
        - October (Folder 8: 10)
        - November (Folder 8: 11)
        - December (Folder 8: 12)
      - 1942
        - January-June (Folder 8: 13)
        - July-December (Folder 8: 14)
      - 1943 (Folder 8: 15)
    - Deposits, 1939-1940 (Folder 8: 16)
    - Inventory, 1940 (Folder 8: 17)
    - Ledgers
      - General. "Ksiega Dziennik Glowna," 1940 April-September (Folder 8: 18)
      - Banque de France, 1939-1940 (Folder 8: 19)
      - Non-budgetary spending and loan fund, 1939-1940. (Folder 8: 20)
        Includes sums related to evacuation
    - Payroll (Box 9)
      - 1938
        - General (Folder 9: 1)
        - List of employees (Folder 9: 2)
      - 1939
        - General (Folder 9: 3)
        - List of employees (Folder 9: 4)
      - 1940
        - General
          - January-March (Folder 9: 5)
          - April-June (Folder 9: 6)
        - List of employees (Folder 9: 7)
    - Preliminary budgets
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 9: 8)
      - 1940-1941 (Folder 9: 9)
    - Receipts payable, 1939-1940 (Folder 9: 10)
    - Relief applications and payments, 1940
      - April (Folder 9: 11)
      - May (Folder 9: 12)
    - Secret funds, 1939-1940 (Folder 9: 13)
  - Biuro Kongresu Potomkow Dawnej Emigracji, 1940 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Consulates
    - General. Preliminary budget, 1940-1941 (Folder 9: 15)
    - Bar-le-Duc, 1940-1941 (Folder 9: 16)
    - Lille
      - General
        - 1939
          - March-July (Folder 9: 17)
          - September (Folder 9: 18)
          - October (Folder 9: 19)
          - November (Folder 9: 20)
          - December (Folder 9: 21)
        - 1940
          - January (Folder 9: 22)
          - February (Folder 9: 23)
          - March (Folder 9: 24)
          - April (Folder 9: 25)
          - June (Folder 9: 26)
          - Preliminary budget, 1940-1941 (Folder 9: 27)
    - Lyon (Box 10)
      - General
        - 1939 (Folder 10: 1)
        - 1940 (Folder 10: 2)
      - Preliminary budget, 1940-1941 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Marseilles
      - General
        - 1939 (Folder 10: 4)
        - 1940 (Folder 10: 5)
      - Preliminary budget, 1940-1941 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Paris
      - General
        - 1939
          - April-September (Folder 10: 7)
          - October (Folder 10: 8)
          - November (Folder 10: 9)
          - December (Folder 10: 10)
        - 1940
          - January (Folder 10: 11)
          - February (Folder 10: 12)
          - March (Folder 10: 13)
          - April (Folder 10: 14)
          - May (Folder 10: 15)
          - June (Folder 10: 16)
      - Preliminary budget, 1940-1941
        - General (Folder 10: 17)
        - Paris library (Folder 10: 18)
    - Toulouse
      - General
        - 1939 (Folder 10: 19)
        - 1940 (Folder 10: 20)
      - Preliminary budget (Folder 10: 21)
  - Projects funded by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1939-1940 (Folder 10: 22)
  - Special credits. Receipts
    - 1939 (Folder 10: 23)
    - 1940 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Travel
    - Expenses, 1940 (Folder 10: 25)
    - Government regulations and circulars, 1936-1941 (Folder 10: 26)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1937-1945 (Box 11)
  - General
    - 1939. (Folder 11: 1)
      Includes letters from Stefan Olpinski-Osten to Adolf Hitler
    - 1940
      - January-April (Folder 11: 2)
      - May
        - 1-15 (Folder 11: 3)
        - 16-30 (Folder 11: 4)
      - June (Folder 11: 5)
    - 1942-1943. (Folder 11: 6)
      Includes correspondence between W. Houwalt and Feliks Frankowski
    - 1943 July. (Folder 11: 7)
      Condolence letter after the death of General Sikorski
    - 1944 (Folder 11: 8)
    - 1945 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Receipts for valuable deliveries, 1937-1940 (Folder 11: 10)
- TELEGRAMS, 1919-1940
  - General.
    Includes instructions letters and reports dispatched in the form of telegrams
    - General
      - General (Folder 11: 11)
      - Beck, Jozef, 1937(incoming) (Folder 11: 12)
      - Diplomatic representations (multiple recipients)
        - 1932
          - Incoming (Folder 11: 13)
          - Outgoing (Folder 11: 14)
        - 1934-1937
          - Incoming (Folder 11: 15)
          - Outgoing (Folder 11: 16)
    - Ankara
      - 1939
        - Incoming, September-December (Folder 11: 17)
        - Outgoing, September-December (Folder 11: 18)
      - 1940 - Incoming, March (Folder 11: 19)
    - Athens
      - 1939
        - Incoming, September-December (Folder 12: 1)
        - Outgoing, September-December (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1940
        - Incoming, January-May (Folder 12: 3)
        - Outgoing, January-May (Folder 12: 4)
    - Belgrade
      - 1939
        - Incoming, September-December (Folder 12: 5)
        - Outgoing, September-November (Folder 12: 6)
      - 1940
        - Incoming, March (Folder 12: 7)
        - Outgoing, March (Folder 12: 8)
    - Berlin
      - General
        - 1932 - Incoming (Folder 12: 9)
        - 1937
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 10)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 11)
        - 1938
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 12)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 13)
        - 1939 - Incoming
          - March-May (Folder 12: 14)
          - July-August (Folder 12: 15)
      - Letters
        - 1937
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 16)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 17)
        - 1938
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 18)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 19)
      - Reports, 1932 - Incoming (Folder 12: 20)
    - Bern
      - General
        - 1937 - Outgoing (Folder 12: 21)
        - 1938
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 22)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 23)
        - 1939 September-December
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 24)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 25)
        - 1940
          - Incoming
            - January-May (Folder 12: 26)
            - July-September (Folder 12: 27)
          - Outgoing
            - January-May (Folder 12: 28)
            - July-September (Folder 12: 29)
      - Letters, 1938, Incoming (Folder 12: 30)
    - Bratislava. Letters, 1937 - Incoming (Folder 12: 31)
    - Brussels
      - General
        - 1932 - Outgoing (Folder 12: 32)
        - 1937
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 33)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 34)
        - 1939 September-November
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 35)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 36)
        - 1940 March-April
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 37)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 38)
      - Letters, 1937
        - Incoming (Folder 12: 39)
        - Outgoing (Folder 12: 40)
      - Reports, 1932 - Incoming (Folder 12: 41)
    - Bucharest
      - General
        - 1937 - Outgoing (Folder 12: 42)
        - 1938
          - Incoming (Folder 12: 43)
          - Outgoing (Folder 12: 44)
        - 1939
          - Incoming
            - September (Folder 12: 45)
            - October (Folder 12: 46)
            - November (Folder 12: 47)
            - December (Folder 12: 48)
          - Outgoing (Box 13)
            - September (Folder 13: 1)
            - October (Folder 13: 2)
            - November (Folder 13: 3)